（环球影业）
（焦点影业）
（安培林娱乐）
出品公司
焦点影业
制作公司
赫拉影业
尼尔街制作公司
安培林娱乐
联合制作
暗影之书
哈姆奈特
（因为“哈姆奈特”与“哈姆雷特”事实上是同一名字）
（在16世纪末至17世纪初的斯特拉特福档案中可以互换使用）
（——《论哈姆奈特之死与〈哈姆雷特〉的渊源》）
【译注: 出自著名学者斯蒂芬·格林布拉特】
原创译制
蒙太奇字幕组
你来了
There you go.
吃吧 你是饿坏了吧
There. You were hungry.
乖孩子
That's it.
（拉丁语）吾必另辟一径
【译注: 正在朗读《农事诗》第三卷】
（拉丁语）自当拔尘于世
（拉丁语）终有一日名扬四海
【《农事诗》: 维吉尔(古罗马诗人)农业诗篇 论耕作与农事纷争】
（拉丁语）吾必另辟一径...
（拉丁语）...终有一日名扬四海
（拉丁语）吾必另辟一径
（拉丁语）自当拔尘于世
（拉丁语）终有一日名扬四海
（拉丁语）吾必另辟一径
（拉丁语）自当拔尘于世
（拉丁语）终有一日名扬四海
（拉丁语）吾必另辟一径
（拉丁语）自当拔尘于世
（拉丁语）终有一日名扬四海
继续念
Repeat.
你好
Good day, sir.
姑娘好
Good day to you.
你来休兰农场来做什么？
What brings you to Hewlands?
来这里教孩子
I'm tutoring the boys here.
教拉丁的先生啊
The Latin tutor.
我听说过你
I've heard of you.
那你来这园里干什么？
What brought you into the garden?
呃...
Uh...
我就随便问问 教书先生
It's just a question, master tutor.
嗯 我 那个...
Yes, I, uh...
就是出来透透气 而且...
I suppose the air was fresh out here, and...
呃 我看到你带着只鸟
uh, I saw you with your bird.
- 那是只鹰 - 哦
- It's a hawk. - Ah.
能上前看看吗？
May I?
别凑太近
Don't get too close.
他没见过你
He doesn't know you.
哦
Oh.
你好 小家伙
Hello, boy.
啊 哈哈哈
Ah.
他喜欢你
He likes you.
你叫什么名字？
What is your name?
别打听
I shan't tell you.
就打听
You shall.
我不说
I shan't.
- 你会说的 - 我不会
- You shall. - I won't.
等我亲你时你就会说了
You'll tell me when we kiss.
你在干什么？
What are you doing?
安妮丝
Agnes.
我叫安妮丝
My name is Agnes.
你家哪儿的？
Where are you from?
我说错话了吗？
Have I said something?
- 啊？ - 没有
- Huh? - No.
- 你不知道我是谁 - 等下 我能去你...
- You don't know who I am. - Wait, I wish to see...
你别再来找我了
You can't see me again.
哦
Oh.
你去哪儿了？
Where have you been?
我下地帮巴塞洛缪
I was in the field helping Bartholomew.
小羊崽病了
A newborn lamb is unwell.
好 我也去地里了
Well, I... I went to the field.
可没见你啊
I did not see you there.
我确实在那儿 巴塞洛缪哥 你给她说说
Well, I was there. Tell her, Bartholomew.
她确实在那里
She was there.
你见过新来的拉丁先生吗？
Have you seen the new Latin tutor?
就是皮匠的儿子
The glover's son.
孩子们说他上着上着课跑掉了 就再没回来
The boys said he just ran out, never returned.
他是来教书还债的
He was supposed to give them lessons
还他父亲的债
to pay off his father's debts.
我没见过他
I haven't seen him.
算了 早该料到
Well, should've known better.
父子都一个德行
Like father, like son.
你们俩可是咱们这教区最美的姑娘
You know, I do believe you are the prettiest girls in the parish.
- 是的 - 将来...
- We are. - One day,
会有许多人上门提亲
I shall have my wits about me
我亲自把关 准把你们嫁个好人家
for all the suitors that will come for you.
安妮丝是大姐 还轮不到我们
Agnes is the eldest. She'll marry first.
她成天往树林里跑 像个流浪女
She will not if she keeps running off to the forest
谁会娶她？
like a gypsy.
- 他们说... - 你去哪儿了?
- When they said... - Where have you been?
我们都等你好几个钟头了
We were expecting you hours ago.
- 我在... - 说啊
- I was... - Well?
我在忙事儿
I was working.
坐下
Sit.
快坐下吧
饭菜都凉了
Your supper's near cold.
- 别闹 别闹 - 别抢
- Uh, boys, boys! - Hey.
- 住手 - 大家都有份 别抢
- Stop. - There's enough for all.
休兰农场那边教得怎么样？
How go the lessons at Hewlands?
那些孩子不是读书的料
Those boys are no scholars.
- 我就纳闷 他们读书有啥用 - 嗯
- I wonder at the notion of all that learning. - Hmm.
注定务农的孩子学拉丁文？
Latin for boys who will be naught but sheep farmers.
- 用来装模做样吗？ - 不 不 不
- It is the putting on of airs. - No, no, no!
- 够了 - 都给你 吉尔伯特
- That will do! - All right, Gilbert.
听你娘的 都有份 别争
You heard your mother. There's enough for all.
你说休兰那帮孩子不好
You speak ill of the boys at Hewlands.
“不是读书的料”
"They're no scholars."
可我跟你说 他们将来...
But I tell you something,
比你更像个男子汉
they'll ever be more of a man than you are.
人家将来有正经活 你没有
They are put to honest work, unlike you.
你没出息 没手艺 只会装模做样
Useless, tradeless, your fancy airs.
读那么多书
All that education,
一点用都没有
not an ounce of sense.
我这没出息的去教书
I'm tutoring those boys to pay
不就是替你还那户人家的债吗？
your debts to that family, am I not?
你欠休兰家那么多债
Your immeasurable amount of debt,
要不是我... 住手
Didn't I help you... Stop!
休兰那边其他人
What of the rest of the family at Hewlands?
你都见过吗？
Have you met them?
只见过那户的母亲
The mother only.
- 那大女儿没见到吗？ - 没有
- Not the eldest daughter? - No.
大家都说 那姑娘是森林巫婆的后代
It is said the girl is the child of a forest witch.
我就见过 她独自走在山路上
I've seen her, wandering the back roads alone
臂上还有只鹰
with a hawk on her arm.
休兰那儿还有鹰？
A hawk at Hewlands?
是的
Yes.
传言说她每次进林都是一个人带着那只鹰
They say she takes him to the forest with her unaccompanied.
你确定吗 伊莱莎？
Yeah, but are you certain, Eliza?
那拿着鹰的是长女 不是仆人？
The eldest daughter keeps a hawk, not a servant girl?
不是仆人 我确定
Yes. Yeah.
安妮丝
Agnes.
你好
Hello.
你跑来这儿干什么？
What are you doing here?
送你个东西
Brought you this.
这是什么？
What is it?
这是...
It's, uh...
给你那只鸟的新手套
it's a new glove for your bird.
我有手套了
I have a glove.
安妮丝
Agnes.
安妮丝 别跑
Agnes, wait.
我认出你了
I know who you are.
那好 我是谁？
Who am I?
好吧 不算了解你 只是听到些传言...
Well, I... I don't know you, but I've heard things...
说我是森林巫婆的女儿？
I'm the daughter of a forest witch?
是啊 村里这么说 但我 我不在意...
Yes. People say that, but I-I don't care...
我可是我母亲的女儿
I am my mother's daughter.
从她那儿学的本事多着呢
I've learnt many things from her.
你瞎看什么？
What are you looking at?
- 看你 - 为什么？
- You. - Why?
- 因... - 你这教书的 不该能言善辩吗？
- I... - I thought you were a man of words, master tutor.
是的
Yes.
- 还难住你了？ - 只是...
- Are you not? - Jus...
我有时很难直接跟人说话
Speaking with people is sometimes difficult for me.
好 那就讲个故事吧
Well, tell me a story, then.
- 讲故事？ - 对
- A story? - Yes.
你想听什么故事？
What story would you like?
起码能打动你自己的故事
Something that moves you.
好吧
All right.
你知道俄耳甫斯和欧律狄刻的故事吗？
Do you know the story of Orpheus and Eurydice?
【译注: 古希腊神话】
俄耳甫斯这个男人
Orpheus is...
有着天赋异禀的音乐才能
a man of music.
他还有着天籁般的嗓音
He has this exquisite voice.
他弹那种七弦里拉 是...
His playing of the kithara, which is a...
是类似竖琴的乐器
is-is a harp-like lyre,
声音美得妙不可言
is so divine,
连天上的鸟儿 地...
birds, the...
地上的走兽 甚 甚至石头和树
the beasts, e-even the stones and the trees,
都能被他的音乐打动随之起舞
they all moved to the rhythm of his music.
后来 俄耳甫斯爱上了一位美丽的山林少女 叫欧律狄刻
Now, Orpheus falls in love with this beautiful nymph, Eurydice.
和山林少女刚结完婚
Soon after their marriage,
她就被毒蛇咬了
Eurydice's bitten by a viper
毒素在她体内迅速扩散
and poison courses through her body,
她就此身亡
and she's killed.
俄耳甫斯悲痛欲绝
And Orpheus, filled with grief,
下到冥府想要将她带回
journeys to the underworld to take her back.
他用琴声迷住了守门的三头犬 刻耳柏洛斯
He charms this three-headed dog, Cerberus.
甚至感动了冥王哈得斯 最终...
He beguiles Hades until finally...
冥王同意了
...he's allowed to take his love back with him
允许把这名女子带回人间 但...
to the world of the living but...
但有一个条件
...under one condition.
什么条件？
What is it?
这名女子必须跟在他身后
She must follow behind him,
而他绝对不能回头看
and he must not turn around to look at her.
现在 他们开始往人间走
Now, as they begin their ascent,
俄耳甫斯却听不见他妻子的脚步声 于是他听啊...
Orpheus can't hear her footsteps, so he listens...
听啊 听啊 一直听
...and listens and listens and listens.
他只听得见自己的心跳
But all he can hear is the sound of his heartbeat.
余下的只有沉寂
And the rest is silence.
当他快到冥门出口时
And as he approaches the gates of the underworld...
他忍不住了
...he can't contain himself any longer.
他回头去看妻子 然后妻子...
He turns around to look at her, and she is...
永远被困在冥府里了
...trapped in the underworld forever.
嗯
Hmm.
这是个好故事
That was a good story.
你喜欢吗？
Did you like it?
艾草者 古之名药也
Remember, mugwort, what you brought to pass,
【《九草咒》: 古英语药咒 列九种草药以驱毒治疫】
世人皆知其德 传颂至今
what you readied at Regenmeld.
其名曰艾 为草之首
You're called Una, the most ancient plant.
能驱三疾 能制三十疾
You defy three, you defy 30,
能解毒气 能散瘴疠
you defy venom, you defy air illness,
能降瘟疫 克之而胜
you defy the horror that stalks the land.
车前草者 草之母也
And you, waybread, plant mother,
根植东方 性禀刚毅
you're open to the east yet mighty within.
遭车碾而不折 遇众踏而复起
Carts creeped over you, women rode over you.
刚柔相济 疗人间之疾苦
You withstood it all, and you pushed back.
你真的能靠摸一个人的手
Is it true that you know everything about a person
看透一切吗？
by touching them here?
并非全部
Not everything.
你摸我时你看到了什么？
When you touched me here, what did you see?
我看见了一幅画面
I saw a landscape.
- 一幅画？ - 嗯
- You saw a landscape? - Mm-hmm.
空洞 黑洞 裂口
Spaces, caves, cliff tops,
暗道和深海
tunnels and oceans,
深不见底 一片漆黑的虚空
this deep, dark, black void,
未知的国度
undiscovered countries.
（拉丁语）天道有常 宿命有律
【译注: 正在朗读《农事诗》第一卷】
（拉丁语）万物难逃衰落之数 消亡乃其必然
（拉丁语）天道有常 宿命有律
她说话了...
She speaks...
她说话了 她说话了
She speaks, she speaks.
且慢
But, soft,
那窗户透出来的是什么光？
what light through yonder window breaks?
那是东方 朱丽叶就是太阳...
It is the east, and Juliet is the sun...
赶走那....
...and kill...
嫉妒的月亮
...the envious moon.
【译注: 正在创作《罗密欧与朱丽叶》第二幕第二场】
你好
Hello.
我要和你成亲
I wish to be handfasted to you.
不 我 我必须和你成亲
No, I... I must be handfasted to you.
非你不可
No one else will do.
我会去跟你继母和你哥哥说
I-I will speak with your stepmother and your brother,
估计他们不会答应
and of course they will not agree, but...
不管行不行就这么定了 不能等了
I don't care because I have no talent for waiting.
哪怕是私定终身
I cannot abide waiting.
那你父母怎么办？
What about your parents?
他们绝不会答应的
Your parents will never agree.
跟我来
Follow me.
等 等 等下
Wait. Wait. W-Wait.
- 跑不掉了 - 别
- No! - No!
我的手套
My glove.
- 是我母亲留给我的 - 哦
- This is my mother's glove. - Hmm.
她源于森林
She came out of the woods...
就像她的母亲一样
...like her mother
像她母亲的母亲一样
and her mother before her.
我家族女人能看到些...
The women in my family see things...
别人看不到的东西
...that others don't.
安妮丝
Agnes.
艾草者 古之名药也
Remember, mugwort,
世人皆知其德 传颂至今
what you brought to pass, what you readied at Regenmeld.
其名曰艾 为草之首
You're called Una, the most ancient plant.
能驱三疾 能制三十疾
You defy three, you defy 30,
能解毒气 能散瘴疠
you defy venom, you defy air illness,
能降瘟疫 克之而胜
you defy the horror that stalks the land.
巴塞洛缪 会好的
Bartholomew, it will heal.
会留疤吗？
Will it make a scar?
可能会 但并非坏事
It may. That's no bad thing.
听
Listen.
听见了么？
Do you hear that?
留心你的梦 安妮丝
You must pay attention to your dreams, Agnes.
梦永远会指引你
They will always guide you.
- 你们好 - 你也好
- Good day. - Good day.
好
Yes.
安妮丝 你怎么在...
Agnes, what's, uh...
你怎么在这儿？
what's happened?
她母亲把她逐出家门了
Her mother has banished her from their house.
她不是我生母 而且...
She's not my mother.
我家那房子归我哥哥巴塞洛缪
The house belongs to my brother, Bartholomew.
我是自愿离开的
I chose to leave.
她有身孕了
She's with child.
哦
Oh.
还说孩子是你的
Says it's yours.
- 真的吗？真是你的吗？ - 呃...
- Is it? Yours? - Uh...
她肚子里的孩子 是你弄的吗？
The child in her belly, did you put it there?
是我
I did.
- 我们已经私定了 娘 - 休想
- We are handfasted, Mother. - We will never allow it!
- 这有什么错啊 - 没我们的同意
- There is no sin in it. - I'm afraid you will need
- 你成不了亲的 - 这有什么错啊
- our consent, and we will... - There is no sin in it!
- 我们决不允许这桩婚事 - 行 行
- ...we will never give it, ever! - All right!
啥？
What?
- 你被她蛊惑了 - 不是的
- You've been bewitched. - No.
我宁愿你当水手送命 也别娶这个巫婆
I'd rather you went to sea than marry this wench.
玛丽
Mary.
不必这样
There's no need for that.
既然他们两厢情愿 这事好解决
I have no doubt we can come to an arrangement.
- 约翰 - 安静 女人
- John. - Hush, woman.
你肯定想在教堂里
I am certain you are eager
看到你妹妹出嫁吧
to see your sister before the altar.
我肯定想现在
I'm certain you'd rather not see your boy
控告你儿子奸淫
dragged before the bawdy court.
没必要闹成那样
There's no need for that.
他们都已经私定了
They said they are handfasted.
嫁不嫁由我说了算
Only if I say so.
嫁给那白面书生到底有啥好处？他有什么用
But why marry a pasty-faced scholar? What use is he?
他的内心比我见过的任何人都深邃
He's got more inside of him than any man I've ever met.
人心是会变的
Everything will change.
你 你也不例外
You. You will change.
我的心已经变了
I'm already changing.
里头太静了
It's too quiet in there.
哪儿里头？
In where?
他们家
That house.
记得我们害怕迷茫时 娘怎么劝咱的吗？
What would our mother say to us if we were afraid or uncertain?
我们要敞开心扉
To live with our hearts open.
别叫它躲在黑暗里
To shut it not in the dark
而是转向太阳
but to turn it to the sun.
他爱的是我本色 不图我变成谁
He loves me for what I am, not what I ought to be.
那就嫁给他吧
Then marry him you shall.
谢谢
Thank you.
艾草者 古之名药也
Remember, mugwort...
来 说跟我一起说 一起说
Say it with me. Say it with me.
世人皆知其德
What you brought to pass,
传颂至今
what you readied at Regenmeld.
其名曰艾 为草之首
You are called Una, the most ancient plant.
能驱三疾 能制三十疾
You defy three, you defy 30,
能解毒气 能散瘴疠
you defy venom, you defy air illness,
能降瘟疫 克之而胜
you defy the horror that stalks the land.
回头看我
Look at me.
安妮丝
Agnes.
嘿
Hey.
看 看那光 那是火
Look. Look at that. Look at the fire.
看看 那是什么啊
Mmm, what's that?
是小狗叼进来的东西
The doggy dragged something in.
快看
There's something.
哦
Oh.
你爹回来了
Daddy's coming.
回来了
Hello.
针脚要小一点
Stitches need to be smaller.
再小 再小一点
M-Much smaller.
对
Yes.
哼
Hmm.
没出息
Useless.
好 再小点
Okay, and now...
再小点
smaller.
- 你去哪儿？ - 我要出去
- Where are you going? - I'm going.
回去干活
Get back to work.
这是你最后一次打我
That was the last time you will ever hit me.
明白吗？
Do you understand?
- 明白吗？ - 明白
- Do you understand?! - Yes.
爱人 该睡觉了
My love, you should come back to bed.
你在写什么？
What are you writing?
不值一提
Nothing of note.
总有值得称道的地方
It's never nothing.
还没写好呢
I don't know.
也许写完会好...
Perhaps when it's finished, it will...
也许吧
Perhaps when it's finished.
念给我听听吧
Why don't you read me what you've written?
安妮丝 这还没...
A-Agnes, it's not--
还没写好呢
It-It's not finished.
没写好
It's not finished.
别敲了 吵醒孩子了
Stop it. You'll wake the baby.
好了
It's okay.
不哭 不哭
No. It's okay.
对不起
I'm sorry.
我喝多了
I've had too much, uh...
安妮丝 我喝多了
Agnes, I've had too much to drink.
我喝...
I've had...
我喝的太多了
I've had too much to drink.
嘿
Hey.
有什么心事吗？
What is it?
我给你的手看看
Give me your hand.
别 别 别 别 别
Pl-Pl-Please, please, please, please,
别 别 求你了 别
please, please, please, please.
- 你怕我看见什么吗？ - 求你了 别
- What are you afraid I will see? - Please stop.
我怕我将来会伤害你
That I am a violent and dangerous man.
不会 你不是那样的人
No, you are none of those things.
- 你怎么能肯定？ - 你是个好人 你是个...
- How do you know? - You're a good man. You're a...
你是个好人
You are a good man.
You're a good man.
难道是后悔跟我结婚了吗？
Is it that you wish that we never wed?
怎么能说出这种话？
How could you say such a thing?
你怎么能说出这种话？
我活着就是为了你和苏珊娜
You and Susanna are all that I live for.
我活着就是为了你们
All that I live for.
- 那到底怎么回事？ - 是...
- What is it, then? - This...
- 来 把手给我 - 停下
- Here. Look at me. - Just stop!
停 停 求你停下 停 停 停
Stop, stop. Please, please, please, please, please, please.
看着我
Look at me.
听着 听着 听我说
Listen. Listen. Listen.
我迷失了
I'm lost.
我找不...
I've lost my...
我找不到方向了
I've lost my way.
我需要 我需要静下心好好写作 安妮丝
I just need to-- uh, Agnes, I just need to work.
他都睡不着觉
He's not sleeping.
- 他对你发火了吗？ - 没有
- Has he ever lost his temper with you? - No.
- 要是他对你动手.... - 没有 他从没那样 从没那样
- If he raises a hand... - No, he has never. He's never.
他只是为自己懊恼
He's angry with himself.
心里难受得要命
He's sick with himself.
他是个好人
He's a good man.
是个好丈夫 也是个好父亲
He's a good husband, he's a good father,
但他还需要更多
but he n-needs more.
他已经有了家和你 还能需要什么？
What could he possibly need other than his family and you?
- 他已经有了你 - 他需要去伦敦
- He has you. - He needs to go to London.
- 伦敦？ - 是的
- London? - Yeah.
为啥去伦敦？
Why London?
因为伦敦汇聚天下
Because London is where the whole world gathers.
说不定能把他爹的手艺带去发扬光大
Perhaps he could extend his father's business there.
- 哎 你又冲动了 - 谁知道他将来会怎样
- Oh, you're being hasty again. - Who knows what he may be...
我不是冲动 他需要更多
I'm not being hasty. He needs more.
- 他只是太闲了 - 他不该呆这小地方
- Well, he needs proper work. - He's not of this world.
给他找个活儿忙起来
The man needs proper work.
- 这小地方能有什么出路？ -  他不能就这么跑掉
- What's in this little town? - He can't just run away.
这小日子 这小地方
This little life? This little thing, it'll...
会逼疯他的
...crush him.
他得离他爹远点
He needs distance from his father.
你跟他一起去伦敦吗？
And you would go with him to London?
不 等他安顿好再说
No, I'll wait until he's settled.
马上家里就会多一口人
There'll be more of us soon.
- 又怀上了？ - 是的
- Another child? - Yes.
夏末时候生
By summer's end.
那现在更不能把他送走了
Then now is not the time to send him away.
那我会失去他的
I'll lose him.
我已经在失去他了
I'm already losing him.
要是送他走 就彻底失去他了
You'll lose him if you send him away.
不 不会的 我肯定我俩的爱能维系得住
No, I know, I know that our love will keep us steady.
求你了 替我跟他爹说说吧
Please. Will you speak to his father?
要是你跟他提去伦敦的事 他会听你的
He'll listen to you if you suggest him going to London.
求你了
Please.
我得找个住处
I should find lodgings.
最好靠河的 离河边皮革场近点
Be near the river, close to the tanneries.
我听说那河水很急
But I'm told that the currents in the river are dangerous
过河要请有经验的船夫
and that you must engage an experienced boatman
每次过河我都照办
every time you cross, and I'll be certain to do that every time,
我保证
I promise.
我会时时刻刻
And I will think of you and Susanna
挂念你和苏珊娜的
with every passing moment.
我会给咱们找个好住处
And I will find us lodgings in London,
到时候在伦敦团聚
and we shall all be together again.
你还没预见出是男孩还是女孩吗？
Do you still not know if it's a boy or a girl?
没有
No.
我也说不清为什么
Don't know why.
你不是说过会有两个孩子陪你到最后吗？
Have you not said that you would always have two children?
是的
Yes.
临终前会有两个孩子在身边
Two children at my deathbed.
第二个能陪你到最后的人来了
Well, then, here is the second.
- 咱们就别道别了 - 好
- We won't say goodbye. - No.
别磨蹭了 快走吧
You get-- Go.
- 你要出门吗？ - 不是 我只是...
- You going somewhere? - No, I'm just...
对 我要去湖边走走...
Yes, I'm going to the lake...
你不许进森林
You're not going to the forest.
- 我非去不可 - 不 你不许去 吉尔伯特快来
- I must. - No, you must not. Gilbert!
你 你得让我去那里
You... you have to let me go there.
- 你必须让我走 - 听我说 安妮丝
- Let me go there! - Listen Agnes.
- 你得放我去 - 河堤已经决口了
- You must let me go! - The river has burst its banks!
- 让我去 - 外面很危险
- Let me! - There is no way...
- 根本没路去森林那边 - 放我走 不要
- There's no way to get to the forest. - Let me! No!
- 我们都为你准备好了 - 我孩子
- We have everything ready for you. - My baby!
不 我 我孩子
No, my-my baby.
我不行
I can't.
生不出来
It isn't coming out.
我没法在这屋里生孩子
I will not have my baby in this house.
没法在这屋
Not in this house.
没法
No.
河水
The river.
- 使劲儿 使劲儿 使劲儿 - 不 不 不
- Hush, hush, hush, hush. Hush. - No, no, no, no.
他说要住河边
He spoke about the river.
河很危险 他可能会被冲走
The river is dangerous. He may be swept downstream!
安妮丝 安妮丝
Agnes. Agnes.
安妮丝 安妮丝 他一切安好
Agnes. Agnes, all is well with him.
你难道忘了他最近的信吗？
Do you not recall his last letter?
别叫了
Stop the screaming.
会把整村人都吵醒的
You'll wake the whole town.
他语气...
He sound...
他语气不对
He sounded different.
不 他带来的是好消息
No, he had good news for us.
- 剧院 - 剧院
- The theater. - Theater.
他和剧团定下来了
He has a contract with the players
- 做剧院用的手套 - 剧院
- to make gloves for the theater. - the theater
安妮丝 使劲儿
Agnes, hush now.
使劲儿 使劲儿 使劲儿
Hush. Hush. Hush.
用力 用力
Bear down. Bear down.
来了 来了
Ah! Ooh!
- 出来了 - 是个男孩
- There we go. - It's a boy.
真好
There we go.
乖孩子 乖孩子
Good boy. Good boy.
是个男孩
It's a boy.
我的儿子
My boy.
谢谢你
Thank you.
怎么回事？怎么了？
What is it? What's happening?
她又要生了
She's starting again.
- 姑娘啊 你怀的是双胞胎 - 来 伊莱莎
- You're having twins, my girl. - Come on, Eliza.
快 抱着他
Here. Quickly.
抱好
Take him.
不 不 不
No, no, no.
我临终前会有两个孩子在身边
Two standing at my deathbed.
我一直以为...
I always believed that it would be...
一直以为是长大的孩子
that they would be my children.
现在我...
And now...
我明白了 原来就是你们俩
now I see it will be you.
得把你扶到产凳上
We need to get you to the stool.
快生了 要生了
It's coming. It's here.
- 不要 - 来 来 起来 起来
- No. - Come on. Come on up. Up, up.
别 我 我不行
Please. I can't... I...
我不行
I can't.
- 来 - 我不该...
- Go. - I should never have...
我不行了...
I can't...
我挺不过去了
I can't make it.
我弄错了 我弄错了
I got it wrong. I got it wrong.
我弄错...
I got it...
他 他不在
He... He's not here.
他 他不在这里
He's... He's not here.
安妮丝 你能行的
Agnes, you can...
你必须行
and you must.
我不行
I cannot.
安妮丝
Agnes.
你能行的
You can...
你会挺过去的
and you will.
你丈夫就在这间屋里出生
Your husband was born here in this room.
他就在那窗边 第一次呼吸
He took his first breath there by the window.
求求你
Please.
求求你 保住孩子
Please let this child live.
一定保孩子 一定
Let this child live. Please.
让他...
Will you let him...
让他回到家后能有孩子陪他
Let him come back and be with his child.
求你了
Please.
让他对我留个好念想
Let him think kindly of me always.
记着我
Remember me.
娘
Mama.
娘？
Mum?
她没抗住
Just too weak.
她承受了很大的痛苦
She was in too much pain.
太可怜了
I mean, poor woman.
越来越痛 她承受不住了
She just got weaker and weaker.
有时候命就是这样
I mean, that's just the way of it sometimes.
她 她大概早就知道这一刻了
She-she must have known the end was nigh.
最好别跟孩子提起她了
Best not speak of her to the children.
再娶一个吧
Safer with a different mother.
孩子都还小
So young.
兴许能忘掉
They may not remember her.
- 娘啊 - 安妮丝 安妮丝
- Mum! - Agnes. Agnes.
- 娘啊 不 - 不 不 安妮丝
- Mama, no! - No, no. Agnes.
孩子 孩子
Child. Child.
- 娘 不要 - 不 不 孩子 孩子 不行
- Mummy, no! - No, no, no. Ch-Ch-Ch-- No.
- 放开我 - 不行
- No! - No.
- 不 让我见娘 - 不 不
- No, let me see her! - No, no!
- 我要见娘 - 不
- Let me see her! - No!
不 娘
No, Mama!
- 安妮丝 - 不
- Agnes. - No!
娘 我要我娘 我要我娘
Mum. I want, I want my mum.
我要我娘啊...
I want my mum...
来了 是个女孩
Oh! Here we go! It's a girl!
是个女孩 她...
It's a girl. She's...
- 等等... - 怎么了？
- It's... Wait. - What?
快点 快点
Come on. Come on.
她怎么不哭？
Why is she not crying?
她没活过来
She lives not.
让我抱抱
Let me have her.
不行 这不吉利
You should not look upon her. It's bad luck.
把她给我
Give her to me.
我会把她安葬妥当的
I'll make sure it gets a decent burial.
把我孩子给我
Give me my child!
【双胞胎: 当时双胞胎被视为怪异现象和不祥征兆】
我的孩子啊
My child.
安妮丝 你有个儿子
Agnes, you have a baby boy.
我把他抱来 你可以喂他
Let me bring him to you, and you may feed him.
女孩已经去了天国
The girl has gone to heaven.
她不会去天国的
She's not gone to heaven.
我母亲去世那晚我发过誓
I made a vow the night my mother died.
我会去你们的教堂 但别指望我开口说什么
I will go to your church, but I shan't say a word there.
【译注: 当时无宗教自由 故以含蓄方式表达不信教】
太好了 太好了 太好了
Yes. Yes. Yes.
你会活下去的
You will live.
我会保护你到底 绝不放手
I will make sure nothing ever takes you away.
我怎么都找不到
I actually couldn't find it.
没有
Hmm.
找到了
Here.
太好了
Perfect.
找到帽子了
I found my hat.
来 对
Okay. Yes.
来 转过去 转过去
Okay, take that side. Take that side.
好
Yeah.
然后系好
And put it around here.
完美
Perfect.
- 哎呀 - 我来吧
- Ooh. Sorry. - Let me help you.
挡到我脸了
It's down my face.
- 跟我学“我是哈姆奈特” - “我是哈姆奈特”
- I'm Hamnet. - I'm Hamnet.
- “我是珠迪丝” - “我是珠迪丝”
- I'm Judith. - I'm Judith.
屋里不准跑
There will be no running in this house.
你们要举止端正 要像...
Conduct yourselves, please, as...
淑女与绅士
gentlewomen and gentlemen.
你们要去哪儿？
Where are you going?
对 他来了 他来了
Yeah. He's-he's coming. He's coming.
回来了
Hello.
你回来了
一看就知道他俩对调了衣服
We all know they've swapped clothes.
咱们什么时候揭穿？
How long are we going to pretend we don't?
只要他们继续演 咱们就不揭穿
We'll pretend for as long as they think they're the same.
你好
Hi.
爹 能再教我下
Father, will you help me with the Greek passage
昨天那段希腊文吗？
from yesterday's lesson?
哈姆奈特 你不是会背了吗？
Hamnet, I thought you'd already learnt it.
我忘了 因为把课本落学堂了
I didn't because I left my primer at school.
好吧 哈姆奈特
Well, Hamnet,
你要用心学
you need to take your studies seriously.
不努力怎么会进步...
How do you expect to improve if you're not...
（希腊语）吾不肯苟且而生 不甘平庸而逝
【译注: 正在朗读荷马《伊利亚特》第22卷】
（希腊语）愿成就丰功伟绩 令后世永传吾名
【《伊利亚特》: 荷马(古希腊诗人)史诗 论英雄 战争与命运】
你们这群小淘气
You rascals.
- 我们耍到你了吗？ - 当然了
- Did we trick you? - Of course you did.
你们又互换来耍我
You swapped places to hoodwink me again.
【译注: 当时女性普遍无法接受正规教育 现实中他妻女都不识字】
苏珊娜 过来
Susanna, come here.
快过来
Come here.
你们还记得要给娘准备的那件事吗？
Now, do you remember the thing we were going to do for your mother?
- 嗯 - 都记得吗？准备好了吗？
- Yeah. - You remember? You ready to do it?
- 嗯 - 好 快去 快去准备
- Yeah. - Okay. Go outside quickly.
快去 快去 快去
Go, go, go, go, go.
- 朝前走 - 别急
- Just step toward... - Wait.
再走 往右走 小心
One st-- Come to your right. Step.
慢点 再迈一步
Step. One more.
- 啥 - 再迈一步
- What. - One more.
咱们三个儿啥时候再聚？
When shall we three meet again?
等打雷 等闪电 还是等下雨？
In thunder, lightning or in rain?
等到这场吵闹都停了 等到这一仗打出个输赢了
When hurly-burly's done, when the battle's lost and won!
那就在太阳落山以前
That will be ere at set of sun.
- 在什么地方？ - 就在荒原
- Where the place? - Upon the heath.
在那儿同安妮丝会面
There to meet with Agnes.
我来了 灰妖猫
I come, Graymalkin.
蛤蟆叫
Paddock calls.
马上到
Anon!
美即是丑 丑即是美
Fair is foul and foul is fair.
美即是丑 丑即是美 美即是丑 丑即是美
Fair is foul and foul is fair. Fair is foul and foul is fair.
美即是丑 丑即是美
Fair is foul and foul is fair.
穿入到...
Hover through the...
【《麦克白》: 出自第一幕第一场 参考卞之琳译本】
演得好
Well done!
真精彩
That was amazing!
挖深点 把土拨到一边
Dig it deep, and then you move all of it to the side,
然后把根放进去
and then you put it down here.
明白吧 然后把土填回去
Right? And then you get the soil around the sides,
用手把土拍平
and then you pat it more.
然后手上就沾了土
And then you get bits like that.
然后两手搓一搓
And you rub it in your hands.
等下 向后退
Whoa. And then back!
照我这样做
Do this.
然后转圈 盯住对手
And when you're doing this, circle.
对 就是这样
Yeah, like that.
准备好了吗？
Ready?
前进 后撤
Forward. And back.
现在 挡剑 挡剑 挡剑
Now, parry, parry, parry.
很好 再来
Good. Again.
接着 我出这招
Now, after that one, I'm gonna do this,
你要闪开
and you get out of the way.
准备好了吗？绕圈走 转动你的剑
Ready? Circle off. Spin your sword.
不对
No.
绕圈 把剑转起来
Circle, spin your sword.
现在 向前迈
Now, come forward.
再往后退
And go back.
挡剑三次
One, two three.
闪开
Out of the way!
非常好 再来一次
Very good. Again.
珠迪丝 闻闻这是什么？
Judith, what's this one called?
- 百里香 百里香 - 是迷迭香
- Thyme. Thyme. - Rosemary.
- 是百里香 - 好吧 百里香 百里香
-Thyme. - Thyme. Thyme.
- 我记错了 - 没关系
- I got it mixed up. - That's okay.
这株是...
This one...
- 这是迷迭香 - 对
- Now, that's rosemary. - Yeah.
迷迭香有什么用处？
And what is rosemary for?
- 放在苹果里一起炖 - 炖苹果
- Putting it in apples. - Apples.
不对 再闻闻
No. What is Rosemary's for?
- 记忆 - 纪念
- Remembering. - Remembering.
对 记忆纪念
Remembering.
现在 搓一搓
Now, you're to rub all this in your hands.
吹个小心愿进去
You blow a little wish.
许个愿 让他带走
To wish him on his way.
明白吗？这就是你和他的小秘密了
Yeah? And it's your secret with him.
看见了吗？
Did you see him?
没看见他在天上吗？
Did you not see him in the sky?
好 再来一次
All right, do it again.
再许个愿
Make another wish.
看 就在上面
Look. Right up there.
就在那里 看见了吗？
Look, just there. Did you see him?
他把你们所有的愿望都藏在他的小心窝里了
And he's got all your wishes tucked in his little heart.
每当想念他的时候
So any time that you want to remember him,
只要吹一下...
you just have to go...
你要去哪儿？
Where are you going?
我要抓到你
Huh? I'm gonna catch you!
I'm gonna catch you!
爹？
Father?
没事吧？
Is all well?
没事
Yes.
听着 别太靠近你爷爷
Listen, I want you to stay away from your grandfather.
他不会打你姐妹 但我担心你
He'll not hit your sisters, but it's you that I worry for,
当我走了你要能保护好自己
and I need to know that you'll be safe when I'm not here.
又要回伦敦了么？
You're going back to London again?
对 明天
Yes, tomorrow.
明天就走？
Tomorrow?
没关系的
It's all right.
这次我们能跟你一起去吗？
Will we go with you this time?
不行 还不行
No, not yet.
嘿
Hey.
我会想念你的
I'll miss you.
但我得走 你明白吗？我得...
But I have to go, you understand? I...
我懂
I know.
我明白
I understand.
那就好
That's good.
你要替我照顾好你娘和你姐妹
'Cause I need you to look after your mother and your sisters.
能做到吗？
Will you do that?
能
Yes.
- 能做个男子汉吗？ - 能
- Will you be brave? - Yes.
真的吗？
Yes?
- 你勇敢吗？ - 是
- Will you be brave? - Yes.
是男子汉吗？
Will you be brave?!
- 是吗？ - 是 是 我是男子汉
- Huh?! - Yes! Yes, I'll be brave!
我很勇敢 我是男子汉
I'll be brave. I'll be brave.
我已经在伦敦替咱们物色好房子了
I've looked at houses for us in London.
- 秋天就要来了 - 嗯
-Autumn is coming. - Mm.
孩子们会生病的
And the children will fall ill.
珠迪丝还是太虚弱了
Judith, she's still not strong enough.
她常常胸闷
She often gets congestion in her chest.
伦敦那空气...
And the air in London is...
去不了
We can't.
但迟早有一天 我们会去的
But one day soon, we will.
我们会跟你去伦敦的
We will come to London with you.
不会的
No, you won't.
你永远不会来的
You'll never come.
夏天你嫌太热
You've waited for the heat of summer to pass...
秋天干燥
...the dryness of autumn,
冬天太冷
the snow and the cold.
你压根儿不信珠迪丝能在伦敦活着
You do not believe that Judith will ever survive London.
你会想尽一切办法保住那孩子
You'd do anything in your power to keep that child alive.
做母亲的不就该这样吗？
Isn't that what a mother is supposed to do?
当然是
Of course it is.
所以...
So...
我决定就在这镇子附近给咱们找个家
...I've decided to look for land outside Stratford.
你和孩子们还在斯特拉特福镇这片生活
That's where you should live with the children.
【斯特拉特福: 距离伦敦160公里 当时为羊毛 皮革等畜产品加工地】
- 谢谢你 - 嗯
- Thank you. - Mm-hmm.
来吧
Ooh!
快过来 啊
Where is she? Ah!
哈姆奈特呢 你来了
Hamnet. There he is.
过来吧
Come here.
爱你 爱你 爱你
I love you. I love you. I love you.
行了 来亲一下
All right. Love you.
- 好了 - 亲一下
- Come on. - Love you.
亲一下
Love you.
哦
Oh.
好吧 过来
All right. Come here.
- 还记得我告诉你的话吗？ - 记得
- Remember what I told you, okay? - Okay.
好孩子
Good boy.
- 我要走了 - 再见
- Bye. - Bye.
- 走了 - 再见
- 真走了 - 再见
- Bye. - Bye.
怎么了 哈姆奈特？
Hamnet?
过来 到这儿来
Come on. Come here.
把手给我
Show me your hand.
你 你看到什么了？
What? What do you see?
我看到你...
I see you.
长大了
Grown.
身强力壮
And very strong.
我还看到你在伦敦 和你父亲一起工作
And I see you in London working with your father.
- 在剧院吗？ - 对
- In the theater? - Yes.
在剧场
At the playhouse.
我会在那儿做什么？
What will I be doing?
你想做什么呢？
What do you wish to do, Hamnet?
我想当个拿剑的演员
I should be one of the players with a sword.
拿剑的？
A sword?
对
Yes.
我想拿剑和其他演员交锋
And I shall clash it against the sword of the other player.
示范给我看看
Show me.
会有场激烈的战斗
There'll be a terrible fight,
观众看得心惊胆战
and everybody watching will be frightened out of their wits.
那谁会赢呢？
And who will win?
自然是我
I shall, of course.
当然是你
Of course you shall.
它们被什么惊到了
Something has upset them.
怎么回事？
What could it be?
可能是天气
The weather?
或者空气里有什么 不确定
Something in the air, perhaps?
告诉琼今天别让孩子们出门了
Best tell Joan to keep the children inside today.
珠迪丝？
Judith?
你在哪儿呢？
Where are you?
醒醒啊
Wake up!
面包师的猫生小猫咪了
The baker told me her cat had kittens.
咱们得去看看
We need to see them.
有八只呢 珠迪丝 八只
There's eight, Judith. Eight!
得抓紧了 要下雨了
We need to hurry. It's going to rain.
珠迪丝？
Judith?
小珠？
Jude?
你怎么了？
What's wrong?
哪儿不舒服？珠迪丝
What's wrong, Judith?
你说话啊 珠迪丝
Judith, answer me.
起来啊
Judith, wake up.
求你了 珠迪丝 说句话
Judith, please. Judith.
- 怎么了？ - 是珠迪丝
- What is it? - It's Judith.
她这样多久了？
How long has she been like this?
我从学堂回来她就这样了
Since I returned from school.
天呐
Oh, my God.
她得上了
She's got it.
是不是？
Hasn't she?
她得了瘟疫
She's got the pestilence.
是不是 娘？
Hasn't she, Mama?
去找你奶奶
Go find your grandmother.
让她马上来
Bid her to come.
快去
Now!
她烧得厉害
She's burning up.
得要水 要很多水
We need, um, more water.
烧大火 把水烧热了
Make a bigger fire and heat up more water.
- 需要热水 - 伊莱莎 去打些水来
- We need warm water. - Eliza, fetch more water
把厨房的白雏菊也拿来
and bring the Bellis from the kitchen.
再拿肉桂
A row of cinnamon.
肉桂能退烧
Cinnamon, that's good for drawing out the heat.
还要松草或者芸香 百里香也要
Pineweed or a rue. Thyme, yes.
去屋里找
You'll find them in the room.
- 娘啊 - 屋里那张桌子边 桌子边
- Mama. Yeah. - The other table. The other side.
娘在这儿呢 我的心肝
Yeah, Mama's here, my love.
来 喝这个 迷迭香熬的药膏
Here, drink this. It's rosemary and jelly.
会没事的 听到没
All will be well, hmm?
都会没事的
All will be well.
珠迪丝 坚持住
Judith, stay with.
娘在这儿 没事的 娘在这儿
Mama's here. It's okay. Mama's here.
大黄 得要大黄 能清肠子
Rhubarb. We need rhubarb to purge the stomach,
能驱瘟疫
drive out the pestilence.
你能去取吗？
Can you go and fetch some?
娘在这儿 没事的 珠迪丝 大家都在
Mama's here. It's okay. Judith, we're all here.
苏珊娜 你也去打些水来
Susanna, draw some water, too.
哈姆奈特和玛丽还有苏珊娜
Hamnet and... and Mary and Susanna.
快去打水
Draw water as soon as you can.
他怎么还没来呢？
Why isn't he here?
伊莱莎 去给你哥哥威廉写信 让他赶快回来
Eliza, go write to your brother and tell him to come.
珠迪丝
Judith.
张开嘴 珠迪丝
Open your mouth, Judith.
张开嘴 娘在这儿 对 很好
Open your mouth. Mama's here. That's it.
好孩子
That's good.
对 会没事的
Yes, you'll be safe.
张开嘴 都喝下去
You'll open your mouth. Drink it down.
喝下去 娘在这儿 别怕 珠迪丝
Swallow it down. Mama's here. It's okay, Judith.
娘在这儿 别怕
Mama's here. It's okay.
没事的
Okay.
安妮丝
Agnes.
你已经尽力了
You have done all that you can.
我绝不会放手的
I will not let her cross over.
奶奶 你失去的三个女儿...
Grandmama, you had three daughters that were taken.
也是像...
Were they...
也是像珠迪丝这样吗？
Were they like Judith?
安妮那时七岁
Anne was seven.
另两个还只是吃奶的婴儿
The other two were just babies.
都长了肿块...
They all had swellings and...
【腺鼠疫: 会导致淋巴结肿大 常见于颈部 腋下和腹股沟】
都发高烧 跟珠迪丝一样
...fever like Judith.
你娘在...
Your mother's trying to...
拼命想保住她的孩子
keep a grip on her child.
没用的
It won't work.
命是天给的 随时都能被收回
What is given may be taken away at any time.
我们得时刻提防着
We must never let our guard down.
千万别把孩子们的...
Never take for granted...
每一次心跳...
...that our children's hearts beat,
每一次呼吸...
that they draw breath,
他们的行走 说话...
that they walk and speak and...
欢笑 吵闹和嬉戏当作理所当然的
...smile, argue, play.
得时刻提醒自己 他们可能说没就没了
Never forget for a moment that they may be gone.
妹妹
Jude.
小珠
别难过
Don't be sad.
你要替我好好活下去
You shall be well.
我不能
I shall not.
没有你我活不下去
Not without you.
它来了
It's here.
妹妹 你看得到吗？
Do you see it, Jude?
它在看着咱们呢
It's watching us.
我要告诉它把咱们都带走
I'll tell it to take us both.
要走一起走
We'll go together.
转过去
Turn away.
它会看错的
It'll make a mistake.
它分不出咱俩谁是谁
It can't tell us apart.
跟我一起呼吸 珠迪丝
Breathe with me, Judith.
我把我的命给你
I give you my life.
你会活下去的
You shall be well.
用我的命换你的 珠迪丝
I give you my life, Judith.
我很勇敢
I'll be brave.
我是个男子汉 爹
I'll be brave, Father.
我很勇敢
I'll be brave.
我是个男子汉 爹
I'll be brave, Father.
我是个男子汉
I'll be brave.
我很勇敢
驭
Whoa.
赶快
Quick as you can.
哈姆奈特
Hamnet.
醒醒 你不该在这儿睡
Hamnet, you're not supposed to be down here.
来 我抱你上楼睡觉去...
I need to take you up to bed.
哈姆奈特
Hamnet.
哥哥？
Hamnet?
娘
Mama.
娘啊
哈姆奈特
Hamnet.
你得张开嘴
You must open your mouth.
会没事的
All will be well.
他在发烧
He's burning.
烧得太高了
He's burning up.
药不起作用 不起作用
It will not sti-- It will not stick!
拿石头 拿石头
A stone. There's a stone.
【有洞的石头: 当时民间信仰认为病气能从一孔进 一孔出】
楼上有块中间有洞的石头
There's a stone upstairs with a hole in the middle of it.
在他床边 快去拿来 快去
By his bedside. Bring it down. I need it.
还要盐 拿盐 得撒盐
And, um, uh, salt. Get salt.
【撒盐: 当时认为能建立保护屏障 驱挡邪灵和病气】
能去拿吗？
Get it. Can you give it?
多拿点盐 有多少拿多少
Can you f-fetch me some salt, as much salt as you have.
水 还要水
Water. We need water.
他 他烧得太厉害了
He's... he's too hot.
太厉害了
He's burning.
我的孩子 娘在这儿
My love. Mama's here.
坚持住 都会好的
All will be well. All will be well.
都会好的
All will be well.
哈姆奈特 别怕
Hamnet, don't be scared.
没什么好怕的
No need to be scared.
都会没事的 娘在这儿
All will be well. Mommy's here.
娘在 没事的
Mommy's here. It's okay.
娘在这儿
Mommy's here.
你看 娘在这儿
Look at me. Mommy's here.
我绝不 绝不会放手的
I will never, ever let you go.
明白吗？
You understand?
娘绝不 绝不会放手的
I will never, ever let you go.
娘的心肝啊
I love you.
心肝啊
伊莱莎 把珠迪丝抱到厨房去
Eliza, take Judith to the kitchen and keep her there.
我不走
Please!
- 我得陪他 - 带她走
- He needs me! - Stay there.
我要陪我哥
He needs me!
我不走
Please!
缬草啊...
Valerian...
哈姆奈特 哈姆奈特 哈姆奈特
Hamnet. Hamnet. Hamnet.
坚持住 坚持住 求你了
Hamnet, you have to stay. Hamnet, please.
哈姆奈特 求你了 你要坚持住 别离开我们
Hamnet, please. You have to stay with us.
娘需要你 我们都需要你
Mama needs you. We need you.
- 住手 够了 - 别离开我们 坚持住 坚持
- Stop! Enough! - Stay with us. Stay, stay.
求求你了 哈姆奈特 坚持住 坚持住
Please, Hamnet. Hamnet, Hamnet, Hamnet.
- 别折腾他了 - 求求你了 哈姆奈特
- Let him alone! - Hamnet, please!
你看不出来吗 太晚了
Can't you see that it's too late for him!
求你了 求你了
Please, please.
哈姆奈特？
Hamnet?
哈姆奈特 哈姆奈特 求你了 哈姆奈特
Hamnet. Hamnet. Please. Hamnet.
我儿子没了
My son is gone.
没了 我的儿子
Just so bereft... it's my son.
没了 我...
I've lost my...
我看灯还亮着 我也睡不着
I saw the light, and I couldn't sleep.
来
Here.
哎呀 孩子 不行
Oh, child, no.
- 不 快去睡觉 - 没事 没事 让她看吧
- No, no, no. Go to bed. - No, no, let-let her stay.
是我害的 娘 都是我害的
It is my fault, Mama. It is my fault.
不 不
No. No.
珠迪丝 这不是你的错
It is not your fault, Judith.
他替了我
But he changed places with me.
他骗了它
He tricked it.
他骗了什么？
He tricked what?
死神
Death.
珠迪丝
Judith.
它来找我时 却把他夺走了
It took him when it came for me.
这话绝对不许再说
Never say those words to anyone ever again.
你哥是因为发烧走的
The fever came for your brother, and it took him.
你想看看他吗？
Do you wish to see him?
想
Yes.
去吧 去看看他
Go on. You can see him.
这真的是他吗？
Is it really him?
是的
Yes.
这 这不像我哥
It-it doesn't look like him.
不
No.
这不是他
It's not him.
不是
It's not.
这不是我哥
It's not him.
天 天还没亮呢
It-It's-it's not morning yet.
还没给他收拾好呢
We haven't prepared him properly.
我来晚了吗？
Am I too late?
- 是你 - 爹
- It's you. - Father.
真的是你
It's you.
真是我
It's me.
儿子呢？
Where is he?
他在哪儿...
Where is...
他在...
Where...
是我儿子
It's my boy.
是我的儿子啊
我没预见到
I didn't see it.
我该多留心哈姆奈特的
I should've paid him more attention.
我一直以为会失去珠迪丝
I always thought she was the one to be taken away
没想到是儿子
when all the while it was him.
我太蠢了
I'm a fool.
不是 没人能救他
No, there's nothing anyone could have done to save him.
你已经尽力了
You did everything that you could.
我是尽力了
Of course I did.
可你人呢？
You weren't here.
我愿把心掏给他
I would have cut my heart out and given it to him.
用我的命换他的命
I would have laid my life down on the ground for him.
- 我懂 我懂 - 可上天不收
- I-I know. I know. - And no one would take it.
- 可你... - 不 你不懂
- But you... - No, you don't know.
你怎么可能懂 你都不在啊
You don't know. You weren't here.
他在折磨中死去
He died in agony.
我...
I...
- 受尽了折磨 - 安妮丝
- He was in agony. - Agnes.
他哭个不停 他哭啊 哭啊
He cried and he cried
-  哭啊 哭啊 哭啊 - 安妮丝 别这样
- and he cried and he cried. - Agnes, stop, stop.
- 他小小的身子在剧痛中抽搐 - 嘘
- And his little body was wracked in pain. - Shh.
不 别让我闭嘴
No, don't shush me.
他当时好害怕
He was so scared.
- 你却没在身边 - 我知道
- And you weren't here. - I know.
我什么办法都用了
I tried everything I could.
我知道你做了
I know you did.
- 我什么都试过了 - 你已经尽了一切
- I tried everything I could. - You did everything that you could.
你已经用尽了一切办法
You did everything that you could.
一切办法
Everything.
安妮丝 安妮丝
Agnes. Agnes.
我会捎信的 安妮丝
I will send word, Agnes.
捎信？
You'll send word?
- 捎给谁啊？ - 给你啊
- To whom? - To you.
我就在这儿啊
I'm here.
我是说到了伦敦我会给你捎信的
What I meant was that I shall send word when I reach London.
伦敦？
London?
我得走了
I must leave.
走？你怎么能走？
Leave? How can you leave?
世界不会因为我们就停下来 安妮丝
The world does simply not stand still, Agnes.
伦敦还有人在等我
There are people waiting for me in London.
演出季马上就要开始了
The season is about to begin,
我们的剧团随时都会从肯特郡回来
and my company shall return from Kent any day now.
我现在就得走了
I have to go now.
现在？
Now?
今天有个商队要出发
There's a traveling party leaving today,
他们有匹多余的马 现在就得走
and they have a spare horse, so yeah.
照看好女儿们 我回来时会...
Look after the girls, and I will return to--
住手
Stop.
别碰我
Don't.
走吧 你走吧
Go. Go.
（哈姆奈特）
“蒙晨暮鼓催岁长”
"When I do count the clock that tells the time,
“夕太沉沉入幽光”
"And see the brave day sunk in hideous night;
“芳草奇花香自散”
"When I behold the violet past prime,
“青丝墨字今已霜”
"And sable curls all silver'd o'er with white;
“繁荫不复幕沧桑”
"When lofty trees I see barren of leaves
“牧群归舍众组忙”
"Which erst from the heat did canopy the herd,
“夏末青禾束成囊”
"And summer's green all girded up in sheaves
“犹似亡魂缠白裳”
"Borne on the bier with white and bristly beard;
“容颜岂非浮云妆”
"Then of thy beauty do I question make,
“终将消散入苍茫”
"Thou among the wastes of time must go,
“芬芳娇艳随风扬”
"Since sweets and beauties do themselves forsake
“新生如笋催人苍”
"And die as fast as they see others grow;
“时光镰刀谁能挡”
"And nothing gainst time's scythe can make defense
“勇敢生育续春阳”
Save breed, to brave him when he takes thee hence."
【十四行诗: 现代编号第12首 以时间流逝与生育为主题】
能再读一遍吗？
Will you read it again?
不了
No.
我已经读了三遍了
I've read it three times.
行了
That's enough.
- 咱们开始拆礼物吧 - 什么礼物？伦敦的吗？
- Shall we do presents? - Presents? from London?
给你的梳子 小珠
A hair comb for you, Jude.
爱惜点用 别弄坏了
Mind you, you'll have to be careful.
这是给你的 安妮丝
This is for you, Agnes.
- 红宝石吗？ - 是的
- A ruby, is it? - Mm-hmm.
从没见过这么漂亮的
It's the finest I've ever seen.
大家都在议论那栋新房子
Everyone's talking about the new house.
那是斯特拉特福镇上最大的房子
It's the biggest in Stratford.
房间多到人进去都能走丢
There are so many rooms. One could get lost.
苏珊娜 那就好好照看好
You shall keep the keys, Susanna.
打理好咱们的房子
You shall manage the house well.
娘 你戴上试试
Put it on, Mama.
你哥巴塞洛缪带你看过那栋房子了吗？
Did Bartholomew show you the new house?
看了
Mm-hmm.
你喜欢吗？
Do you like it?
你怎么不亲自带我去看的？
Why didn't you show me yourself?
是怕我不愿离开吗？
Were you afraid I wouldn't leave?
因为哈姆奈特死在这个房子里
'Cause Hamnet died here in this house.
我一直在想他在哪儿？
You know, I'm constantly wondering where he is.
他去了哪儿？
Or where he has gone.
不管我做什么 脑子里都是他在哪儿？
Whatever I'm doing, I'm wondering, "Where is he?"
他不能就这么凭空没了啊
I mean, he can't have just vanished.
我一定要找到他
All he needs is for me to find him.
他肯定在哪个地方
He must be somewhere.
都一年了还是这样 我真害怕自己会疯掉
I fear I may run mad with it, even now, a year on.
一年算什么啊
A year is nothing.
一年什么都不是 每时每刻...
A year is nothing. It's every second...
每分每秒 每天每年
every minute, every day.
我们怎么可能停止寻找啊
We may never stop looking for him.
对不起 安妮丝
I'm sorry, Agnes.
听到了吗？我说对不起 安妮丝
Did you hear me? I said that I'm sorry, Agnes.
- 为什么道歉？ - 为这一切
- For what? - For everything.
- 你被那地方缠住了 - 为...
- You're caught by that place. - For...
- 什么地方？ - 你脑子里那个地方
- What place? - That place in your head.
对你来说 那地方比什么都好
It is now more real to you than anywhere else.
连咱儿子死了都留不住你
Not even the death of our child can keep you from it.
哈姆奈特死了
Hamnet died.
死得很惨
A horrible death.
你本该在场
And you should have been there.
你本可跟他道个别
You could have bid him farewell.
你看到了什么？
What do you see?
什么？
Hmm?
什么都没有
Nothing.
什么都没有？
Nothing?
什么都没有
Nothing at all.
好吧
Oh, well.
你还是回伦敦吧
You should go back to London.
不用为我们操心
You need not concern yourself with us.
没有你我们的日子也照过
Get along just fine without you.
“这句话从前是个似是而非的悖论”
This was sometime a paradox,
“如今已被时间所证实”
but now the time gives it proof.
“我确实曾爱过你”
I did love you once.
“没错 殿下 您确实让我信以为真”
Indeed, my lord, you made me believe so.
“你当初就不该相信我”
You should not have believed me,
“美德嫁接到我们这罪恶的老树干上 也...”
for virtue cannot so inoculate our old stock for...
“你当初就不该相信我”
You should not have believed me,
“美德嫁接到我们这罪恶的老树干上”
for virtue cannot so inoculate our old stock
“也结不出好果”
but we shall relish of it.
“我从未真爱过你”
I loved you not.
“那我真是被深深欺骗了”
I was the more deceived.
“去美人庵吧”
Get thee to a nunnery.
【美人庵: 指女性宗教修行场所 又为妓院俚语 此处含贬低之意】
“干嘛非得生出一堆罪人来？”
Why wouldst thou be a breeder of sinners?
“我自己还算个老实人”
I am myself indifferent honest,
“但我的罪过却多得数不清”
but yet I could accuse me of such things
“最大的莫过于...”
that it were better to...
重来
Again.
“去美人庵吧”
Get thee to a nunnery.
“干嘛非得生出一堆罪人来？”
Why wouldst thou be a breeder of sinners?
“我自己也算个老实人 但...”
I am myself indifferent honest, but...
重来 是“我自己还算个老实人” 重来
Again. "I am myself indifferent honest." Again.
“我自己还算个老实人”
I am myself indifferent honest,
“但我的罪过却多得数不清 最大的莫过于”
but yet I could accuse me of such things that it were better
- “我娘把我生了出来” - 重来
- my mother had not borne me. - Again.
“我这个人...”
I, myself...
- 呃... - 再来
- And... - Again.
“我这个人...自己还算个...”
I, myself, am indifferent...
是“我自己”
"I am myself."
“我自己还算个老实人”
I am myself indifferent honest,
“但我的罪过却多得数不清...”
but yet I could accuse me of such things that it were...
再来
Again.
“但我的罪过却多得数不清...”
But yet I could accuse me of such things that it were...
重来
Again!
“我自己还算个老实人”
I am myself indifferent honest,
“但我的罪过...”
but yet I could accuse me of such...
你根本没投入
You are simply mouthing the words!
我自己还算个老实人
I am myself indifferent honest,
但我的罪过却多得数不清
but yet I could accuse me of such things
最大的莫过于我娘把我生了出来
that it were better my mother had not borne me.
我这人自傲 报复心强 野心大
I am very proud, revengeful, ambitious,
肚子里装的那些坏主意
with more offenses at my beck
多到我都数不清
than I have thoughts to put them in,
想都想不尽 干也干不完
imagination to give them shape or time to act them in.
像我这样的人
Now, what should such fellows as I do
在天地之间苟活 有什么用？
crawling between heaven and earth?
我们全是烂透的坏人
We are arrant knaves all.
你可千万不要信我们
Believe none of us.
去你的美人庵吧 重来
Go thy ways to a nunnery. Again.
生存...
To be...
还是毁灭...
...or not to be...
这是个问题
...that is the question:
哪种更高贵？是默然 忍受...
Whether 'tis nobler in the mind to... suffer
命运投来的巨石...
The slings and arrows of...
射来的毒箭？
...outrageous fortune...
还是...
...Or...
挺身反抗...
...to take arms against a...
汹涌的苦海...
...sea of troubles,
通过斗争...
And by opposing...
渡向彼岸？
...end them.
♪ 我祈求那些树啊 ♪
♪ I pray that those trees ♪
♪ 还我男孩来 ♪
♪ Will return my boy ♪
♪ 只因... ♪
♪ For ♪
♪ 那只温柔的知更鸟 ♪
♪ Sweet bonny Robin ♪
♪ 是我仅有的幸福 ♪
♪ Is all my joy. ♪
【《我那去了绿林的知更鸟》: 英国民谣 绿林象征身后世界 知更鸟象征逝者】
安妮丝？
Agnes?
我 我碰巧来镇上
I... I was in town, and I...
就想顺路来看下你
I thought I would pay you a visit.
听说你公公约翰去世了 替你们难过
I was very sorry to hear about John's passing.
你丈夫还好吧
How's your husband?
失去父亲 真是件悲痛的事啊
It's a... it's a terrible thing to lose one's father.
他好得很
He's well.
忙得要命 还在搞一出喜剧
He's very busy. He's preparing a comedy.
他的新剧可不是喜剧
His new play is not a comedy.
是悲剧
It's a tragedy.
你应该早知道了
But you knew that.
镇上人人都在谈论
Everyone in town is talking about it.
我是劝过你别嫁给他...
I did warn you about marrying him...
别装作疼我
Don't pretend that you care for me.
你不是我娘 永远也不是
You are not my mother, and you never were.
再见 安妮丝
Good day, Agnes.
他都好几个月没跟我们联系了
He's not spoken to us for months.
他怎么能
How could he...
他怎么能不告诉我们呢？
How could he not tell us?
你不想看看吗？
Do you not wonder what is in it?
看什么？
In what?
（《哈姆雷特的悲剧》）
这剧
The play.
你们找谁呢？
Who are you looking for?
威廉·莎士比亚
William Shakespeare.
我们是他的家人 从斯特拉特福来的
We're his family from Stratford.
上楼 他住阁楼
Go up the stairs. He lives in the attic.
拥有斯特拉特福最大房子的人
Why would the man with the largest house in Stratford
怎么会住在这样的地方？
be living here?
我不明白
I don't understand.
我以为...
I thought...
我以为他...
I thought he...
我该怎么办？
What shall I do?
敞开心扉
Keep your heart open.
（天下皆为舞台）
【拉丁格言"天下皆为舞台 人人都是演员" 莎士比亚《皆大欢喜》亦用此意象】
【译注: 当时剧场分为站票 看台 包厢等级】
（《哈姆奈特的悲剧》）
- 谁呀？ - 不 先回答我
- Who's there? - Nay, answer me:
出来 报上名来
stand and unfold yourself!
国王万岁
Long live the king!
【国王万岁: 执勤人员碰头暗号】
伯纳多？
Bernardo?
要是碰到我的夜班同伴
If you do meet Horatio and Marcellus,
霍拉旭和马塞拉斯 叫他们速来
The rivals to my watch, bid them make haste.
他们好像来了 站住 谁
I think I hear them. Stand, ho!
是谁？
Who's there?
它今晚又现身了吗？
Has this thing appeared again tonight?
- 我还没看见 - 霍拉旭说...
- I have seen nothing. - Horatio says...
这演的什么啊
What are they talking about?
这不过是我们的幻觉
...'tis but our fantasy...
我曾和他说过 他就是不信...
...and will not let belief take hold of him touching...
这和我儿子有什么关系？
What has any of this to do with my son?
我们已经见过两次这可怕的景象...
...this dreaded sight twice seen of us...
他们很害怕
These men are frightened.
有什么好怕的
Of what?
别不信 让我们再给你解释一遍...
And let us once again assail your ears...
他们在提防一个幽灵
They watch for a ghost.
昨天这个时候 北极星西侧的星到这个位置时...
...when yond same star that's westward from the pole...
幽灵？
Ghost?
钟刚好敲了一下...
...The bell then beating one...
快住嘴 别说了
Peace; break thee off!
看 它又现身了
Look where it comes again!
一模一样 就像那位已故的先王
In the same figure, like the king that's dead.
看 它阔步离去了
See, it stalks away!
那是他
That was him.
谁能告诉我 为什么...
...Tell me why this same...
- 那是威廉 - 嘘
- That was Will. - Shh.
- 他不是演员 - 不 不
- He's not in the play. - No, no.
那幽灵就是威廉演的
It was Will as a ghost.
刚才向我们显灵的那位先王
Our last king, Whose image but now appeared to us,
正是那场决斗中 英勇的哈姆雷特国王...
Was dared to the combat; our valiant Hamlet...
哈姆雷特
Hamlet.
你听到了 你听到了吗？
Did you hear... did you hear that?
听到了
Yes.
他们念了 念了他的名字
They said his-- they said his name.
安妮丝
Agnes.
- 安妮丝 别 - 让开
- Agnes, wait. - Out of my way!
安静
Please be quiet.
他们干嘛念他的名字啊
Wait, did they say his name? Huh?
别自找苦吃
Do not upset yourself.
他凭什么 凭什么喊我儿子的名字？
Why is-- Why did he use his name?
- 他当他谁啊 - 安静
- I don't know him. - Quiet.
...依我之见
...and by my advice,
不如将我们今晚所见
Let us impart what we have seen tonight
禀告给年轻的王子...
Unto the young prince...
不许念我儿子的名字
Don't you dare pronounce my son's name!
闭嘴
Quiet!
...对我们沉默的幽灵 会对他说话
...dumb to us, will speak to him.
虽说大家对我亲爱的王兄死讯
Though yet of our dear brother's death,
还记忆犹新
The memory be green,
但我们要节哀顺变
Yet so far hath discretion fought with nature
在深切缅怀他的同时
That we with wisest sorrow think on him,
也要为我们自身着想啊
Together with remembrance of ourselves.
我受不了 我不能再看下去了
I will not stay a minute longer to be a part of this jest.
- 别急 再看一会儿 - 我的侄儿
- Wait. One moment. - ...my cousin.
- 不 我要回家 - 哈姆雷特
- No. I want to go home. -  Hamlet...
【哈姆雷特: 原著中先王与王子同名皆为哈姆雷特】
现在也是我的儿子
and my son...
你怎么还一脸愁云？
How is it that the clouds still hang on you?
我的好哈姆雷特 脱去这沉重的黑衣
Good Hamlet, cast thy nighted color off.
别总是低眉垂眼的
Do not for ever with thy vailed lids
仿佛要从尘土中寻出你高贵的父亲
Seek for thy noble father in the dust.
万物有生必有死
All that lives must die,
顺其自然 谁都会踏入永恒
Passing through nature to eternity.
是啊 母后 这确实是常理
Ay, madam, it is common.
但我心中的郁结
But I have that within which passes show.
远非这些丧服哀装所能表达
These are but the trappings and the suits of woe.
固执地沉溺于哀伤
To persevere In obstinate condolement
是一种逆天的愚行
is a course of impious stubbornness.
这不是堂堂男子的悲伤
'Tis unmanly grief.
是对天意的违抗
It shows a will most incorrect to heaven.
哦
Oh.
真想这 这沉重的肉体消融
This too, too solid flesh would melt,
化为晨露消散
Thaw and resolve itself into a dew.
真想永恒的真神
Or that the Everlasting had not fixed
未曾禁止自杀这罪孽
His canon gainst self-slaughter.
这就是一座荒芜不治 杂草丛生
'Tis an unweeded garden That grows to seed;
长满毒花恶草的花园
things rank and gross in nature possess it merely.
谁曾料到啊
That it should come to this.
才死了两个月
But two months dead--
不 还没满两个月
nay, not so much, not two--
那是一位多么杰出的国王 如同太阳神
So excellent a king, that was to this
而现在这位 却像只肮脏的禽兽
Hyperion to a... a satyr.
你要领我上哪儿去？
Whither wilt thou lead me?
快说 我不跟你走
Speak. I'll go no further.
我是你父亲的灵魂
I am thy father's spirit,
被判在夜间游走于这大地
Doomed for a certain term to walk the night,
白天则要忍受地狱烈火的焚烧
And for the day confined to fast in fires.
我的时辰快到了
My hour is almost come
我又得回到硫磺的火焰中...
When I to sulfurous and tormenting flames
去遭受痛苦的煎熬
Must render up myself.
- 唉 可怜的幽灵 - 不 不要可怜我...
- Alas, poor ghost. - No, pity me not...
你只要留心听着我要告诉你的话
...but lend thy serious hearing to what I shall unfold.
听好
List.
听好 啊 听好了
List, oh, list.
要是你曾深爱过你的父亲
If thou didst ever thy father love...
天呐
Oh, God.
且慢 我仿佛闻到了清晨的气息
But soft, methinks I scent the morning air.
我长话短说 那天我照常在花园里午睡
Brief let me be. Sleeping within my orchard.
你叔父趁我熟睡之际偷溜进来
Upon my secure hour, thy uncle stole
拿着一瓶天杀的剧毒毒液
With juice of cursed hebona in a vile,
灌入了我的耳朵
Within the porches of my ears did pour
这麻风病般的毒液...
The leprous distillment...
毒性之大 嗜血如仇
...whose effect Holds such an enmity with blood of man
它顺着血管流动得比水银还快
That swift as quicksilver it courses through
流遍全身七窍八脉
The natural gates and alleys of the body.
突然一下子
And with a sudden vigor it doth posset
就凝固了我的血...
And curd, like...
像卤水点豆腐一样
...eager droppings into milk,
把我健康的血液彻底摧毁了
The thin and wholesome blood.
我就这样被毒害了
So did it mine.
转眼间我全身长满了烂疮...
A most instant tetter barked about...
如癞病般浑身长满可憎的痂皮
...Most lazar-like, with vile and loathsome crust,
体无完肤
All my smooth body.
啊
Oh.
惨呀
Horrible.
哦 惨啊 太惨了
Oh, horrible. Most horrible.
只要你还有人性 就不要再忍了...
If thou hast nature in thee, bear it not...
他成了我们的儿子
He has swapped places with our son.
回头看我
Look at me.
萤 萤火虫的微光已经暗淡
The... the glowworm shows the matin to be near,
黎明就要来了
And 'gins to pale his uneffectual fires.
我的儿子啊
My boy.
再会了
Adieu.
记着我
Remember me.
生存还是毁灭
To be, or not to be,
这是个问题
that is the question.
哪种更高贵？是默然忍受
Whether 'tis nobler in the mind to suffer
命运投来的巨石 射来的毒箭？
The slings and arrows of outrageous fortune,
还是挺身反抗汹涌的苦海
Or to take arms against a sea of troubles
通过斗争 渡向彼岸？
And, by opposing, end them.
死了 沉睡了
To die, to sleep,
就那样了
No more.
要是一场睡眠可以终结
And by a sleep, to say we end
我们这些血肉之躯生来要承受的
The heartache and the thousand natural shocks
万千苦难 那可是天大的好事
That flesh is heir to-- 'tis a consummation
是求之不得的结局
Devoutly to be wished.
死了
To die,
沉睡了 没准还有梦呢
To sleep, perchance to dream.
啊 这就是问题
Ay, there's the rub.
摆脱了这凡尘肉体 在那死亡的沉睡中
For in that sleep of death, what dreams may come
我们会做什么梦
When we have shuffled off this mortal coil
这必然令人踌躇
Must give us pause.
正是这份顾虑
There's the respect
让我们心甘陷入这漫长的苦难
That makes calamity of so long life.
谁甘心忍受这人世的鞭挞和嘲辱
Who would bear the whips and scorns of time,
压迫的屈辱
The oppressor's wrong,
傲慢的蔑辱
the proud man's contumely,
心碎的羞辱
The pangs of despised love,
法律的冷辱
the law's delay,
官吏的欺辱 以及小人对
The insolence of office, and the spurns
勤勤恳恳老实人的侮辱
That patient merit of the unworthy take,
否则当一把匕首就能解脱
When he himself might his quietus make
谁不愿意？
With a bare bodkin?
谁愿背负这重担
Who would fardels bear,
撑着这疲惫的身躯呻吟 流汗
To grunt and sweat under a weary life,
要不是死后那无人归返
But that the dread of something after death,
未知的国度令我们恐惧
The undiscovered country from whose bourn
困扰了我们的意志
No traveler returns, puzzles the will,
使我们宁愿忍受眼前的不幸...
And makes us rather bear those ills...
各就各位
En garde!
一剑
One!
不 没有击中
No! No!
中了 很明显的一剑
A hit, a palpable hit!
我们的儿子一定会胜利
Our son shall win!
- 好吧 再来 - 格特鲁德 别喝
- Well, again! - Gertrude, do not drink.
又是一剑 你自己说中没中
Another hit! What say you?
吃我一剑
Have at you now!
王后怎么了？
How does the queen?
她肯定是晕血了
She swoons to see them bleed.
不 不 是那酒 那酒
No, no, the drink, the drink!
啊 我心爱的哈姆雷特
Oh, my dear Hamlet.
我中毒了
I am poisoned.
啊 恶毒的阴谋
Oh, villainy!
喂 把门锁上
Ho, let the door be locked!
奸贼 揪出来
Treachery! Seek it out!
哈姆雷特 奸贼就在这儿
It is here, Hamlet.
哈姆雷特 你也要死了
Hamlet, thou art slain.
没有药能救得了你
No medicine in the world can do thee good.
你活不到半个钟头了
In thee, there is not half an hour's life.
都是国王做的孽
The king's to blame!
剑头也有毒药？
The point envenomed, too?
那么好 毒药 也给你
Then, venom, to thy work!
你这个乱伦的 血腥的丹麦的魔王
Here, thou incestuous, murderous, damned Dane!
给我喝...
Drink...
喝下这杯毒酒
Drink off this potion!
你那心爱的珍珠在里面吗？
Is thy union here?
【心爱的珍珠: 具双关 既指原著中的珍珠 又指婚姻】
跟我的母亲一道去吧
Follow my mother.
我死了
I am dead.
可你还活着
Thou livest.
请将我的故事与大义
Report me and my cause aright
如实告知尚不知情的人吧
To the unsatisfied.
若你曾对我怀有深情与敬重
If thou didst ever hold me in thy heart,
暂且别去享那极乐
Absent thee from felicity awhile,
留在这残酷的尘世 隐忍着痛苦
And in this harsh world draw thy breath in pain
去把我的故事讲清
To tell my story.
啊 我要死了
Ah, I die!
这剧毒正夺去我的意志
The potent poison quite o'ercrows my spirit.
余下的只有沉寂
The rest is silence.
导演
赵婷
编剧
玛姬·欧法洛
改编
自玛姬·欧法洛同名小说
《哈姆内特》
制片人
丽莎·马歇尔
皮帕·哈里斯
尼古拉斯·贡达
制片人
史蒂文·斯皮尔伯格
萨姆·门德斯
执行制片人
克里斯蒂·麦克斯科·克里格
赵婷
劳里·博格
联合制片人
玛姬·欧法洛
卡罗琳·雷诺兹
摄影指导
乌卡什·扎尔
艺术指导
菲奥娜·克隆比
剪辑
赵婷
阿方索·贡萨尔维斯
服装设计
马尔戈西亚·图尔赞斯卡
音效
约翰尼·伯恩
配乐
马克斯·李希特
选角指导
妮娜·戈尔德
主演
杰西·巴克利 饰 莎士比亚妻子安妮丝
保罗·麦斯卡 饰 安妮丝丈夫威廉·莎士比亚
主演
艾米丽·沃森 饰 莎士比亚母亲玛丽
乔·阿尔文 饰 安妮丝哥哥巴塞洛缪
主演
雅各比·朱佩 饰 儿子哈姆奈特
奥利维娅·莱恩斯 饰 小女儿珠迪丝
主演
贾斯汀·米切尔 饰 安妮丝继母琼
大卫·威尔莫特 饰 莎士比亚父亲约翰
主演
路易莎·哈兰德 饰 安妮丝生母罗文
弗蕾亚·汉南-米尔斯 饰 莎士比亚妹妹伊莱莎
波德希·雷·布雷斯纳赫 饰 大女儿苏珊娜
主演
诺亚·尤佩 饰 《哈姆雷特的悲剧》戏中哈姆雷特王子
赵婷
导演作品
字幕译制
蒙太奇字幕组
字幕贡献者
翻译/校对/时间轴/后期：小p
后期/时间轴：NickCollect
特别感谢
朱生豪, 卞之琳, 梁实秋
傅光明, 党晟, 孙大雨 等翻译家
莎士比亚学家：Stephen Greenblatt
语言学家：Joseph S. Hopkins
多个在线研究项目
以及《哈姆奈特》电影和小说的所有参与者
本故事是对莎士比亚文学遗产的多层致敬。
草药意象直接呼应《哈姆雷特》中欧菲莉亚的悲剧台词；
男孩女孩的换装设定则致敬了
《威尼斯商人》《皆大欢喜》和《第十二夜》中的经典桥段；
而安妮丝列出的多个意象
（空间、洞穴、悬崖、隧道、大海、虚空与未知国度）
亦呼应了莎翁多部作品中常见的主题。
鉴于娱乐性与学术性的平衡考量，
本作翻译以剧情呈现为主，
尊重导演的创意表达，
对莎翁文学深层意义的阐释有限，敬请理解。
欢迎加入我们的 Telegram / IRC 社群深入交流讨论
@MontageSubs
蒙太奇字幕组
字幕许可 CC BY-NC-SA 4.0
♪ 我的知更鸟啊 飞向了那绿林 ♪
♪ My Robin to the greenwood will go ♪
♪ 那里有橡树也有白蜡 ♪
♪ Where the oak and the ash ♪
♪ 还有那尖刺的荆棘 ♪
♪ And the briars do grow ♪
♪ 爱人啊 你可好啊 ♪
♪ How fares my love ♪
♪ 夜幕吞噬了森林 ♪
♪ As the darkness falls ♪
♪ 深陷那幽闭的树影里 ♪
♪ There within ♪
♪ 你可好啊 ♪
♪ Those tangled walls? ♪
♪ 爱人啊 你可好啊 ♪
♪ How fares my love ♪
♪ 夜幕吞噬了森林 ♪
♪ As the darkness falls ♪
♪ 深陷那幽闭的树影里 ♪
♪ There within ♪
♪ 你可好啊 ♪
♪ Those tangled walls? ♪
♪ 绿林啊 近在咫尺 ♪
♪ The greenwood is near ♪
♪ 绿林啊 又远在天边 ♪
♪ And the greenwood is far ♪
♪ 无数的危险啊 ♪
♪ And many a danger ♪
♪ 潜伏在那里 ♪
♪ Befalls a man there ♪
♪ 我祈求那些树啊 ♪
♪ I pray that those trees ♪
♪ 还我男孩来 ♪
♪ Will return my boy ♪
♪ 只因那只温柔的知更鸟 ♪
♪ For sweet bonny Robin ♪
♪ 是我仅有的幸福 ♪
♪ Is all my joy ♪
♪ 我祈求那些树啊 ♪
♪ I pray that those trees ♪
♪ 还我男孩来 ♪
♪ Will return my boy ♪
♪ 只因那只温柔的知更鸟 ♪
♪ For sweet bonny Robin ♪
♪ 是我仅有的幸福 ♪
♪ Is all my joy. ♪
（焦点影业）
蒙太奇字幕组 (MontageSubs)
用爱发电 ♥ Powered by Love